<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of Sir Alan Broderick, Kt. who dyed at Wandsworth in the county of Surrey, on Thursday, November 25th, and was interr'd there on Friday, Decemb. 3d., 1680 / by Nathanael Resbury ... .</title>
            <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36714</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15987965</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15987965</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104694</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57059)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of Sir Alan Broderick, Kt. who dyed at Wandsworth in the county of Surrey, on Thursday, November 25th, and was interr'd there on Friday, Decemb. 3d., 1680 / by Nathanael Resbury ... .</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Broderick, Alan, --  Sir, d. 1680.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LVII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104694:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104694:1"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>St. JOHN BRODERICK</hi> Kt. AND THE Reſt of the Worthy Relatives OF Sir ALAN BRODERICK Kt. DECEASED.</head>
            <p>HOW unfit a Perſon I am to make my firſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in publick, in a Diſcourſe of ſo Excellent a Man as your Brother was, You your ſelf may beſt judge, who ſo well have known both Him and Me. You knew Him equal to what the beſt Mind could think, and (I had almoſt ſaid) beyond what the beſt Tongue could ſpeak of Him. And you know me, ſo little and inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant a thing, that, if the World were to take the meaſures of good Reports from the Perſon that makes them, the Perſon repreſented would be an huge ſufferer. <q>
                  <hi>Non eget auxiliis, nec defenſoribus iſtis.</hi>
               </q> He needed not, (becauſe he deſpis'd and was above the tickle of being known and fam'd in the World) but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the Pencil that gave ſo lively a touch upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Mr. <hi>Cowley,</hi> a Perſon that both knows ſenſe, and alſo how beſt to expreſs it in his own <hi>Mother tongue.</hi> As to what hath been endeavour'd by Me, that it ventures abroad beyond the compaſs of our own <hi>Pariſh-Church,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:104694:2"/>it muſt be charg'd, partly upon my own forwardneſs to ſhow my reſpects in ſaying ſomething, though ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath him; and partly your Complement in telling me it was worth the while; but chiefly the inſtance of ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that had heard, and either did themſelves, or ſuppos'd others might lye under the prejudice of ſome ſlanders, which the malevolent humour of this Age may have affixt upon his Name. I mean chiefly as to his living or dying in the <hi>Romiſh Faith.</hi> Indeed, had it pleas'd the All-wiſe God to have reſtor'd him to Himſelf and the World from this laſt ſickneſs, it would have been very needleſs for any one to have added one tittle to the Memoires of himſelf, which he would have bleſt us with in his own hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. For, having taken notice what entertainment thoſe Remarks upon the Lord <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s death did generally meet with, and that all his Religious breathings were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by ſome the raves and delirancies of a ſick brain; by others, a ſubtle fetch at laſt, to take off the ſtench of his name, and entitle all his former lewdneſſes at leaſt to the Charity of good minds, ſo as they ſhould forget them in the joy they conceiv'd at his pretended change: and by moſt, a pang of horror upon his Conſcience under the terrors of death: either of which, if believ'd, might effectually hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the advantages that ſuch examples otherwiſe do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally yield; Your excellent Brother (I ſay) having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd this; did reſolve (and that at a time when neither Himſelf nor any of us had any ſuſpicions but that he was returning to a good ſtate of health again to have given the World a publick account in his own unmatchable way of
<pb facs="tcp:104694:2"/>thinking and expreſſion, the ſentiments he had of Religion both as to the Faith and Practice of it. This, he not only made me hope and expect upon my firſt ſuggeſting the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediency of it; but afterward hinted it to a much more
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. Heze Burton.</note> valuable Perſon upon a viſit he gave him; wherein (by the way) the Dr. profeſt, he never found the joy and pleaſure of two hours throughout the whole courſe of his life, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to what had tranſported him from that kind of diſcourſe he had then been entertain'd with by Sir <hi>A. Broderick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, though it hath pleas'd God in his unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table wiſdom to prevent ſo uſeful a teſtimony from himſelf, and it is ſo weakly undertaken by a very unſuitable Pen, yet I hope the truth of what is ſaid will make ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation for want of the niceneſs and elegancy of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure. And as to the truth and credibility of what is here avow'd, I hope the ſolemn proteſtation which I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventur'd to make in the body of the Sermon, will even yet juſtifie it, though we live in an Age wherein the great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Jeſuitiſm</hi> hath appear'd in that effroncy, as to harden the minds of Criminals to palliate their Treaſons under ſuch ſolemn Oaths at the laſt periods of Death it ſelf, that it may for the future almoſt deſecrate all due veneration to that great Sanctuary of Truth, and render it even uſeleſs amongſt men.</p>
            <p>Be it as it will, I knew the ſubject uncapable of flattery, and therefore gave my ſelf the larger ſcope of commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe I knew my ſelf ſtill within the limits of what he deſerv'd. For certainly he was ſuch an one whoſe bulky ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue bore no proportion to his little ſtature, but it had quickly
<pb facs="tcp:104694:3"/>invaded and overſwell'd all the parts of it, as <hi>Statius</hi> ſpeaks of little <hi>Tydeus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> 1. <hi>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eb.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>— <hi>Totos infuſa per artus</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Major in exiguo regnabat corpore virtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing more, I think my ſelf bound to account for; and that is, that whereas I ſay in my Sermon, that for ſome years before the cloſe of his days, he engag'd in the beſt thoughts and in the beſt practices of life; I would thereby deliver him from the diminiſhing imputation of a death-bed repentance. It was not the dread and terror of that which Nature ſo eaſily ſhrinks at, that govern'd him in this change of life, but the juſt ſenſe and reaſonings in his own mind, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd and cultivated by the Grace of God, that had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd him in a well-temper'd reſolution of future devotion toward God and uſefulneſs toward Men.</p>
            <p>He oftentimes told me, that he had not naturally that dread and horror for Death, that ſeem'd in the tempers and conſtitutions of ſome Men: even then, when (as he expreſt himſelf) God knows, he had all the reaſons imaginable, to have trembled every joynt at the fears of a ſurprize, he had no more perplexing apprehenſions of Death, than of that fly, which in the inſtant of his ſpeaking, was moving upon his hand. In his laſt ſickneſs, as there was nothing unuſual that for a long time gave himſelf or his friends any concernment for the iſſue of it ſo when any threatning ſymptoms did grow upon him, he ſeem'd to be under no fright at them; ſo that neither before, nor in his ſickneſs was it fear, but choice that made him what he was.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, there was a very remarkable Feaver two or
<pb facs="tcp:104694:3"/>three years before his death, that had given us nearer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of loſing him, than this laſt had done till the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cloſe of it; and this did indeed faſten in him the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions he had antecedently taken, of being more uſeful and exemplary in his Generation, if God ſhould ſpare him; which we all viſibly experienc'd in that remainder of time wherein we afterward enjoyed him. He made it evident that his ſick-bed goodneſs was not <hi>as the Morning dew which paſt away</hi> upon the warmth and vigour of his health again, but remain'd &amp; exerted it ſelf ſtill in <hi>more fruit,</hi> to the laſt minute, wherein he was capable of acting like himſelf. I cannot omit one very conſiderable paſſage he told me of, and which he had made a very thoughtful obſervation of himſelf; and that was, that he had taken notice, how for a long time after he had begun to bethink himſelf, he gave himſelf a task of conſulting the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures every day, eſpecially ſome portion in the Pſalms, which he always had a peculiar veneration and eſteem for, as believing there was ſomething therein that might well ſuit every circumſtance and condition of life, which a man, dependant upon Providence, could ſuppoſe himſelf in in this World; and for which reaſons he did with ſo much eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſult &amp; embrace that uſeful and learned Paraphraſe which a Reverend Dignitary in our Church hath lately put forth;
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick</hi> D.P.</note> beſides thoſe moſt Religious and valuable Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the late <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Clarendons,</hi> which he had by him in Manuſcript. And yet, he told me, he obſerv'd, that in the daily road of abſolving this task wherein he had oblig'd himſelf, he found ſo little more than ordinary as to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:104694:4"/>concern or emotions of his mind, that he could not but think that all this performance was but what we charge the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> for reſting in, the meer <hi>opus operatum,</hi> in Religion, wherein he could not be ſatisfied; and therefore made it his importunate requeſt in his private retirements to God, that he might in conſulting his Oracles, find ſome other reliſh and ſavour upon his ſpirit ſome other tranſports of mind, which, he thought, without the blemiſh of any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Enthuſiaſm, he might expect as the ſignature and ſtamp of Divinity in what he read. This, he often prayed for, and this, as he himſelf believ'd he found ſome good effects of, ſo might his obſerving friends eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if they took notice but of his outward deportments in any action where the Publick Prayers, or the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures had their ſhare.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall give you no further trouble in enlarging up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other heads wherein I might find ſufficient matter, that would be pleaſing to my ſelf, and uſeful to others. And, as I dare not reflect upon the conducts of Providence, who hath thought fit to ſnatch ſuch an one from us that had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted himſelf ſo much to his ſervice and our advantage, ſo I earneſtly pray for you his Relatives and mine own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that we may ſo remember his example as to follow it, where he follow'd Chriſt's, that when we depart we may be with Chriſt, as we hope and believe he is.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithful and obedient Servant,</hi>
Nathanael Resbury.</signed>
               <dateline>WANDSWORTH, <date>
                     <hi>Decemb. 24. 1680.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104694:4"/>
            <head>A FUNERAL-SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 57.</hi> v. <hi>1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>The Righteous periſheth, and no man lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHether (as ſome Interpreters have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectur'd) it was a peeviſh and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable exception that <hi>Solomon</hi> made, againſt the vain and worthleſs ſtate of humane life, or whether it was a ſober and inſtructive remark he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, from the obſervation he had taken of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and undiſtinguiſh'd fate both of the <hi>fool,</hi> and <hi>wiſe man;</hi> yet is it ſo certain and undeniable a truth, that (in part) it might proclaim a vanity upon all the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perfections of <hi>Humane Nature</hi> (conſider'd only in this preſent ſtate of life) what he telleth us, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.16. <hi>There is no remembrance of the wiſe, more than of the fool for ever, ſeeing that which now is, in the days to come ſhall be forgotten: and how dyeth the wiſe man?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104694:5"/>as the fool.</hi> He had obſerv'd that after all the embel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhments of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Art,</hi> when any one perſon by the moſt induſtrious improvement of his <hi>Native</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages had been labour'd into a wonder of his Age, as to all the <hi>real</hi> accompliſhments of <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> yet the ungentle hand of Death can by one ſtroke wipe out the well-drawn Scheme like the Sponge upon the Slate, and make the Carkaſs of that wiſe and elevated piece of Mankind, as uſeleſs and inſignificant, as the Wretch that had drivel'd out his life in perfect Ideotiſme and unapprehenſiveneſs: when the Man by a long, and happy enquiry into all the deſirable ſecrecies of Knowledge hath made ſo choice and uſeful a collection of thought, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes as well the <hi>delight,</hi> as the <hi>Oracle</hi> of Mankind; he hath then no ſecurity, but that ſickneſs, and his fate may in a few moments befool and baffle all theſe improv'd and heighten'd intellectuals: <hi>His breath go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt expreſſeth it) <hi>he returneth to his earth,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.4.</note> and in that very day all his thoughts periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may make the ſame obſervation, if we take this <hi>wiſe man</hi> and this <hi>fool</hi> under the notion wherein <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and other parts of the Holy Scriptures have often repreſented them, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>vertuous,</hi> or the <hi>vitious</hi> and <hi>profligate</hi> man; the <hi>excellency</hi> of the one, and the <hi>worthleſneſs</hi> of the other, are undiſtinguiſh'd (at leaſt) as to the certainty of death; <hi>there is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge in that war:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 8.8.</note> As is the good ſo is the ſinner, and he that ſweareth as he that feareth an oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An inſtance whereof even in this two-fold notion of Wiſdom we have at this preſent before us whiles we are doing our laſt office to this <hi>Great,</hi> this <hi>Good</hi> man, whoſe cultivation in all the acquirements and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Nature may give us <hi>Solomon</hi>'s reſentment,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104694:5"/>alas! <hi>how dyeth the wiſe man? as the fool:</hi> and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary luſtres of whoſe Religion and vertue (the only real and valuable Wiſdom indeed) may juſtly awaken in us the complaint our <hi>Prophet</hi> makes in the words of my Text, <hi>The Righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and merciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not here enquire into the occaſion or intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of theſe words, nor undertake to determine, from the various gueſſes of Expoſitors, whether the Prophet more directly intended any one ſignal and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious perſon, <hi>e. g. Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> himſelf, or indeed the frequent deceaſe of Good and Excellent men in general, the loſs of whom, as it was of preſent miſchief and diſadvantage to thoſe that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd them, ſo did it ſeem an <hi>omen</hi> and <hi>preſage</hi> of a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitous Age, from the miſeries of which, it had pleas'd the Divine Providence, to draw off thoſe that had been peculiarly endear'd to him.</p>
            <p>It may ſuffice for our purpoſe that the <hi>Prophet</hi> makes his complaint in theſe two Obſervables.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Nations loſs and deprivement of ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſon or Perſons, whoſe excellency, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the greatneſs of their loſs, is intimated in a double character which may comprehend their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Piety toward God, and their uſefulneſs and deſirableneſs toward men: <hi>The Righteous periſheth and Merciful men are taken away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He reſents the ſtupidity and ſenſleſneſs of the Age and Nation, that regard not ſuch unlucky and preſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging events; they neither apprehend the preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies and miſchiefs of ſuch a loſs, nor think at all how ill and portentous an aſpect the Death of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104694:6"/>ſuch Men may have to future calamities. Though <hi>the Righteous periſheth, yet no man layeth it to heart,</hi> though <hi>merciful men are taken away, yet none will conſider</hi> the impendent evils they might reaſonably upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion expect; <hi>they do not think that the Righteous is taken away from the evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might from both theſe Obſervables, engage in a very uſeful ſubject of diſcourſe, by ſhewing in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Death of Good men, where it is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitated, and hath not in it the unavoidable reaſons of Nature and old Age, may be juſtly accounted a ſevere and deplorable infliction of Providence; it is a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement and act of Divine judgment upon the Place or Nation that is thus depriv'd of them. This might be argued from manifold advantages of ſuch Mens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode and continuance amongſt us: Partly what might reſult from the influence of their good examples; the minds of Men being indeed more eaſily ſhap'd and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell'd into a conformity of goodneſs by <hi>Example</hi> than by <hi>Precept:</hi> and Religion deriving its viſible encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and countenance from the exemplary lives of ſuch Men, it takes off that vicious modeſty and ſhieneſs that ſome have of being ſingular, and makes them more confident and chearful in doing well, when they ſee others do ſo too.</p>
            <p>But further, beſides the influence of Good example I might urge the advantage of Good men's Prayers while they are in this World. Their Prayers, like the <hi>Ark</hi> in <hi>Obed-Edom's houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> 6.11.</note> do frequently ſecure a <hi>bleſſing</hi> within their circuit and ſphere of action. It is an expreſſion it pleaſes God himſelf to uſe by his Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> that when the Nation of the <hi>Jewes</hi> had made themſelves ſo deeply obnoxious to God, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104694:6"/>he found himſelf immediately provok'd to ruine them; <hi>I ſought for a man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>among them that ſhould make up the hedge, and stand in the gap before me for the Land, that I ſhould not deſtroy it: but I found none. Ezek.</hi> 22.30. And thus we find <hi>Moſes</hi> actually preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent by his interceſſion, ſo as to divert the ſtroke when it had almoſt fallen upon the provoking <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to their utmoſt deſtruction, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. <hi>à</hi> 9. <hi>ad</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the advantage of Good men's continuance amongſt us might be argu'd from their active and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual uſefulneſs in the whole courſe and tenor of their lives, the zeal and gravity of their inſtructions may help to correct and inſtitute the manners of ſome, the ſobriety and juſtice of their actions to rebuke and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince others: in a word, their mercifulneſs and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (for it is the property of ſuch, to <hi>go about doing good</hi>) may diſperſe it ſelf to the feeding of the hungry, the clothing the naked, protecting the oppreſſed, and relieving the univerſal want and indigency of the neighbourhood. But for theſe things; I muſt ſatisfie my ſelf only with a tranſient hint and glance at them. Nor ſhould I indeed ſo much as mention them, but that they directly ſubſerve to the purpoſes of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It might be further remark'd, how portentous and preſaging a thing it is, and points toward a Deluge and inundation of miſeries upon that place, where Good men are frequently, or immaturely call'd off. It is a ſign (according to what is intimated in the Text) that Providence through the foreſight it hath of the approaching ſtorm ſecures a ſhelter beforehand for the fondlings of his care and indulgence; that he is not willing (according to what <hi>Abraham</hi> once pleaded in <hi>Sodom</hi>'s behalf) <hi>to deſtroy the righteous with the wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.23.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104694:7"/>and ſo is beforehand removing the obſtacles and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints of his vengeance that without the interpoſure of any <hi>moving</hi> and <hi>compaſſionable</hi> object, he might take his full <hi>blow.</hi> It is like <hi>Noah</hi>'s houſing in the <hi>Ark</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the old World could be drown'd:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1.</note> or the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans quitting <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and retirement to <hi>Pella</hi> before the <hi>Roman Arms</hi> could perfect their victory upon that Place and Nation. This might lead into a large Field of collection both from the Holy Scriptures and other Hiſtories that would illuſtrate this argument, how the deſtruction and overthrow of whole Communities hath trod upon the heels of the unripe and unlucky death of the beſt men in it; but the limits of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hour muſt preſcribe againſt it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, As conſequent to the foregoing obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I might reflect, how ſtupid and unreaſonable a diſregard it is to the chaſtiſement and diſcipline of Providence, where while he thus deals, in removing the beſt and cull'd part of his <hi>Creation</hi> amongſt us, we do with no reſentment or concern bewail and deplore the misfortunes or ill boadings of ſo great a loſs.</p>
            <p>And now, how far we are concern'd in what hath been hitherto only glanc'd at; give me leave to lay ſome claim to a due and juſt thoughtfulneſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment of mind amongſt thoſe of you who have liv'd within the reach of this Gentleman's diffuſive goodneſs and uſefulneſs. It becomes the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> whatever the ſullen <hi>Stoick</hi> might pretend to in ſome of the peculiar maxims of his <hi>ridiculous, impracticable,</hi> (I may add) <hi>inhumane Philoſophy;</hi> It becomes (I ſay) the Chriſtian ſometimes to recount the weight and moment of theſe afflictive incidencies of life that grieve and diſeaſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104694:7"/>
Let me pay that juſt debt to the Memory of him who is ſnatch'd from us, and inſinuate the due reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and awe you ought to entertain for the frowns and diſpleaſure of him who governs the World, by inſiſting a little upon the nature and quality of our loſs, and giving you, as much as I am capable, the image and repreſentation (though in a very rough and unskilful draught) of the Perſon whom we are now depriv'd of. And here I am ſo very well aſſur'd beforehand againſt all danger of <hi>flattery</hi> (the ſubject it ſelf having attain'd ſome degrees, which my mean and crippled thought and expreſſion cannot reach) that whoever intimately knew him will be recollecting ſomething ſtill, which I ought not to have denied him the Glory of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the firſt place therefore I might be very well allow'd to begin with that uſual head of Panegyrick where the ſubject could well bear it, <hi>viz.</hi> the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his Birth and Extract, and ſo give you his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neage in a long Series of Worthy and Honorable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtry, who from time immemorial had liv'd in the Regiſtry of Honour in the <hi>Northern</hi> parts, till his own Father, by the occaſion of a Noble truſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lieutenancy of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> came to add warmth to our <hi>Southern</hi> clime, and bleſs'd this place not only with his own and his Religious Lady's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Vertues (whoſe Names and Memories are ſtill fragrant in thoſe odours of goodneſs wherein they had been ſo plentifully ſcented in life) but with a numerous and valuable Progeny, amongſt whom was this Wonder both of <hi>Greatneſs</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> Alas! that I muſt ſay he was! —<hi>Hinc illae lachrymae.</hi> But I am afraid I ſin againſt the humble intention and deſign of our <hi>Honourable Friend,</hi> ſo much as in mentioning his Extract; this being a theme of boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104694:8"/>which he ſo much deſpis'd, that he could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble it even in his laſt <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Testament,</hi> wherein he hath made expreſs proviſion that his Herſe ſhould by no means be garniſh'd with the uſual Ornaments of a Family, and no Eſcutcheon ſhould either there or elſewhere appear. Perhaps having that opinion of vulgar admiration and gazing, with the <hi>Moraliſt,</hi> that it ſo little adds to the value of him whom in ſuch trifles they admire, that it is a ſymptom of madneſs in the wonderer:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arr. in Epict. L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Who are thoſe you would be admired by? are they not ſuch whom you were wont to call madmen? and will you be ambitious of the opinion of a madman?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It would add ſenſe to the affliction of our loſs, could I tell you what treaſures of Knowledge were ſhipwrack'd when this Veſſel ſplit. But for me to endeavour a commendation here, would be almoſt as ridiculous, as for the <hi>Pigmee</hi> to pretend to an hiſtory of the <hi>Gyants,</hi> reckoning he had told you of Prodigies of ſtature, when he had rais'd the <hi>Gyant</hi> ſome few inches meaſure beyond himſelf. I muſt profeſs my ſelf in an Orb ſo many Regions below what this Great man was fixt in, that it might have been as reaſonable for himſelf when alive, to have pretended to add luſtre to the Angels in deſcribing their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as for me to greaten his Name by telling what a Maſter in all the parts of <hi>Science</hi> he was. Yet give me leave to ſay ſomething, who have for ſome years been gleaning after His mighty Harveſt.</p>
            <p>Certainly this Age, though more fertile in the <hi>Sons of Wiſdom</hi> than former Ages perhaps have been, yet cannot exhibite many beyond this <hi>Gentleman</hi> in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104694:8"/>whom there was ſo happy a conjuncture of quickneſs and ſharpneſs of <hi>Wit,</hi> with maturity and ſtrength of <hi>Understanding;</hi> comprehenſiveneſs and tenaciouſneſs of <hi>Memory,</hi> with choice and diſcretion of <hi>Judgment,</hi> that is not uſual, I may ſay, hardly repeated in any one inſtance again. His <hi>Memory</hi> was under that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and empire of <hi>Judgment,</hi> that it never loſt a Jewel committed to its keeping, and the Judgment ſo well skill'd and faithful that it would never cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that great Repoſitory with a <hi>trifle</hi> or <hi>counterfeit.</hi> He had ſo clear and diſtinct a ſenſe of things, that, though he had travell'd all the Regions of <hi>Learning,</hi> yet had never bewilder'd himſelf, and though he had amaſt a treaſure of very heterogeneous materials, yet were they all ſo orderly and methodically diſpos'd, that he could fetch from every proper Cell what might be moſt <hi>delightſome</hi> or moſt <hi>uſeful</hi> in all the varieties of Converſation he maintain'd; and as he had been a mighty devourer of Books, ſo his very <hi>diſgorgings</hi> (if I may uſe the word) had generally more reliſh than the firſt <hi>cookery:</hi> becauſe his judgment had pick'd out and thrown away all the needleſs and ſuperfluous mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before he would deign a repetition: that to Me, his cenſure either of Books or Men (which yet had always its candid leaning and byaſs) ſeem'd a very juſt cynoſure and ſteerage in my choice or neglect of them. He, if any, hath made void that old obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Aliquis in omnibus, nullus in ſingulis.</hi> In <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,</hi> there was no old or new hypotheſis, but he had ſo well digeſted (ſo far at leaſt as became the Majeſty of ſo great a Mind to condeſcend to the little ſports of conjecture) that he could with all eaſineſs either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain or redargue it. In <hi>Anatomy,</hi> he could almoſt talk as wondrouſly as he was made. In <hi>Poetry</hi> he had ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104694:9"/>choice a collection in memory, and ſo lucky an art in uſing it for the cheer of converſation, that both the ancient and modern Poets liv'd in him, and when he had any juſt occaſion to bring them into Company, he gave them a dreſs ſo decent and ſuitable, that their wit through all the changes of Ages and Humour did ſtill, when introduc'd by him, appear modiſh and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionable. In <hi>History,</hi> he was ſo univerſally accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht as to all its parts, eſpecially <hi>Topographical</hi> and <hi>Chronological;</hi> that if any imputation can be upon his memory, it muſt be upon his modeſty and reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this particular, that he hath not made ſome eſſays in Hiſtory (to which he might equally have pretended with any one Author extant) wherein he might have given Laws as to method, and his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as to credibility in the ſallacious or diſputable reports of Antiquity. Neither let me paſs over in an ingrateful ſilence the advantages my ſelf have reap'd from him, as to that knowledge that lies directly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſphere of mine own function; for in <hi>Divinity</hi> he was ſo throughly vers'd, that he could give a ſtrict account of (though he had no delight in) the Wars and controverſies of it, and had determin'd himſelf in the <hi>Truth,</hi> not becauſe he knew not the <hi>Errors,</hi> but becauſe he knew and could argue that they were ſo. But, as the <hi>Polemick</hi> part in <hi>Divinity</hi> had made him ſo uneaſie that he almoſt contemn'd the <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> whoſe method of dogmatizing he though had been, if not the <hi>original,</hi> yet at leaſt the <hi>Nurſery</hi> of theſe jars and contentions in the Church; and could not but bewail the ſhort and imperfect inſight that Humane Nature it ſelf was allow'd in this World, by which the beſt minds could not <hi>think the ſame things,</hi> nor hardly bear with each other in their <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences;</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104694:9"/>ſo, thanks be to God, I dare ſay, that for ſome conſiderable time before the cloſe of his days he was a zealous and exemplary proficient in the <hi>practick part,</hi> and made it his buſineſs not only to <hi>think</hi> and <hi>talk</hi> theſe <hi>great</hi> things, but to <hi>live</hi> them too.</p>
            <p>And I am glad I am now entred this beſt Scene of his life, that I can in the terms of my Text tell you that the <hi>Righteous</hi> and the <hi>Merciful man is taken from us;</hi> I pray God forbid the Omen, that <hi>he is taken from the Evil to come!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, as to all that I have hitherto ſaid, Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (under the ſenſe he had of greater things) was ſo ſlenderly opinionated in ſuch lower accompliſhments, (For he was (if in any thing) <hi>affected,</hi> in deſign'd and ſtudy'd <hi>unaffectedneſs</hi>) that had not the beſt and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of him taken flight beyond the diſturbances of what happens in this Mortal ſtate, it would find it ſelf uneaſie, that ſuch contemn'd and neglected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks of praiſe ſhould be mention'd or inſiſted on, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the eſtabliſhing of his value amongſt Men.</p>
            <p>And becauſe my Text points to a twofold Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in a Perſon, that may render the death of ſuch an one, a common misfortune and calamity: I ſhall direct my Diſcourſe with reſpect to both of them, as they were eminently viſible in him. The firſt Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> the other is <hi>mercy:</hi> Under the former; I ſhall conſider his <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Devotion</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God. Under the latter, his <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>uſefulneſs</hi> toward Men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to his Religion; his Profeſſion was that of the Reform'd, as the Doctrine and Diſcipline of it is eſtabliſht in the <hi>Church of England</hi> by Law: which he took care to leave upon Record in his laſt <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Testament.</hi> And indeed it is no nice or impertinent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104694:10"/>fineneſs in this <hi>calumniating</hi> Age to leave ſome unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Memorial of what Faith we dye in, becauſe there is a <hi>factious party</hi> on the one hand, who are too apt to brand all actions not done in direct and zealous favour to them, with the odious and reproachful name of <hi>Popery;</hi> and there is a <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> trick on the other hand, to enroll the flower of Wit, or Learning, or Wealth and Intereſt within the Diptychs of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church,</hi> that when ſuch are dead and cannot ſpeak for themſelves, or when ſtrangers to them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the <hi>number</hi> and <hi>weight</hi> of ſuch Names, they may be intic'd or frighted into a cloſure with that <hi>party</hi> which hath ſo plauſible an appearance, and whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt ſeems ſo ſtrong and invincible.</p>
            <p>But as to our <hi>Friend</hi> whoſe worth would almoſt make the ambition of that Church venial, to pretend to a ſhare in him; I have heard him upon occaſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſo great an abhorrence and deteſtation of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Religion, that he hath profeſt <hi>he could bear the imputation of being Mahumetan or Atheist rather than a Romanist;</hi> that is, he would not be accounted ſo much a fool as to eſpouſe principles ſo foppiſh ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly baffled by the very <hi>infancy</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ſo deſtructive of common ſence, &amp;c. But, if the World had no other Religion to pretend to, but ſuch an one, he would utterly renounce all. He could not but believe that he had <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>eyes,</hi> he could both <hi>feel</hi> and <hi>ſee,</hi> and therefore would not take a <hi>Wafer</hi> for his <hi>Redeemer:</hi> nor could he imagine the God he ought to worſhip had ſuch a reliſh to bloud, that he delighted to have his Worſhip introduc'd or ſecur'd by Rebellion or Murder, by open Wars, or ſecret Maſſacres, the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Inquiſition, and all kind of Barbariſm. The <hi>Turk</hi> he thought ſomething more plauſible <hi>as leſs cruel,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104694:10"/>and the <hi>Atheist</hi> more excuſable <hi>as not ſo abandon'd a fool.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, thanks be to God, he had no reaſon to flye to either the one or the other, for want of the <hi>reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> or <hi>gentleneſs</hi> and <hi>good nature</hi> of Religion, for he found and lov'd and practis'd it in <hi>ours.</hi> And indeed ſo ſteddy and devoted a Member was he to <hi>this Church.</hi> that in the publick figure he once made in the World, he did moſt ſenſible ſervices to its intereſt, which ſome nearlieſt concern'd can never forget; and that ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from all ſelfiſhneſs, that he could not without ſome indignation reject a mighty thankſigiving-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which the gratitude of ſome had prompted them to make to him: Nor would he afterward interpoſe his intereſt in behalf of Relation or Friend; leſt it might ſeem an intimation or remembrance of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices he had done; unleſs in one inſtance not long ſince, wherein the zeal and fervour of his love made him make one unſeaſonable requeſt, and the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of his friendſhip made him reſent the diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment with ſomething a leſs candour than he was wont to interpret things; His <hi>love</hi> having ſo far by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſs'd his <hi>judgment</hi> at that time, that he could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what the wiſdom of thoſe with whom he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded did diſcern, as to the <hi>worthleſsneſs</hi> and <hi>inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficancy</hi> of him for whom he had ſolicited. So much may ſerve as to what Profeſſion he made.</p>
            <p>As to His Practice: This for ſome years laſt paſt (to which my ſelf have been an eye-witneſs, and a joyful obſerver) hath been ſo ſignally Religious, that as in none of the excellent endowments, I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready mention'd, He was of the ordinary rank, ſo, herein (how late ſoever he ſet out) yet when he once began the courſe, he made ſuch large and nimble ſteps
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104694:11"/>Heaven-ward, that he out-ſtrip'd the ordinary Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that had begun long before in ſelf-denyal and the zeal of his Devotions, in Circumſpection and Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs over his actions and thoughts, in largeneſs of mind both for and toward God, in all the exerciſes of a deep and ſerious repentance, and in all the noble rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings of faith beyond what is obſervable in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtages of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>I will readily acknowledge (and why indeed ſhould I ſcruple to own what himſelf with ſuch repeated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and brokenneſs of ſpirit would to all ſober ears ſo freely and heartily condemn himſelf for?) that a long Scene of his life had been acted off in the Sports and Follies of ſin: if I may uſe his own words, it was a <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Abandon'd</hi> way he had ſometime purſu'd, Scepticiſm it ſelf not excepted, wherein the poinancy of his Wit, and the ſtrength of his reaſoning (even in that very argument, the uſing of which proclaims a Man, in the Language of the Holy Scriptures, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fool) may have been the occaſion of a great deal of miſchief towards ſome that are already gone to their accounts without the happy retreat that himſelf made; and others who may yet ſurvive him, and ought to improve the goodly example he hath given them, of reſcuing themſelves from thoſe ruinous il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, wherein their miſopinionated wit, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful charms of their own Luſts have hamper'd and entangled them.</p>
            <p>But I mention theſe things, and I hope all good minds will entertain them with that kind of Joy, which the <hi>Angels</hi> themſelves are ſaid to expreſs at the <hi>converſion of a ſinner, Luke</hi> 15.7, 10. A Joy (if I may ſo ſpeak) that had been wanting in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> had it not been for the recovery of ſome <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104694:11"/>Wanderers on Earth; a pleaſure which the Indulgent <hi>Father</hi> could not have conceiv'd, had not the <hi>prodigal Son returned to himſelf and him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We live, I confeſs, in an Age wherein Credulity is the leaſt of our Crimes; we are not eaſily induc'd to believe any thing, but what perhaps ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive wheadles from the <hi>common enemy</hi> may whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper and inſinuate; ſo that it is not an eaſie matter to poſſeſs Men with any aſſur'd perſwaſion of the truth of ſuch an inſtance, when we come to tell them of the mighty change and amendment of ſuch as have been remarkable in Vice. Even good Men themſelves think it their prudence to queſtion ſuch an event, as hardly comporting with ſo perverſe and naughty an Age as this is; and Ill men apprehend it their intereſt to ridicule and laugh ſuch a ſtory out of the belief of others, leſt a new Monument ſhould be erected to their ſhame; and ſo on both ſides it is entertain'd either as the dawbs and flattery of the <hi>Narrator,</hi> or the diſguiſes and perſonatings of the <hi>Penitent,</hi> deſigning only a good fame, and to leave a perfum'd Name behind him. It hath been the fate of a late <hi>Noble Perſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">E. of Roch.</note> who having quitted the ſtage of this World with an action far different from the entry he made upon it, being indeed a Prodigy of Converſion from the extremes of ill, to the extremes of good; the incredulity of moſt Men hath given ſuch modeſty to the Reverend Perſon that could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the whole with great truth and aſſurance, that he hath been almoſt aſham'd to endeavour that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the World. I pray God grant we may none of Us live to ſee the day, wherein the fooliſh Legends of ſome Rebel and Dunghil-Saints may not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104694:12"/>be obtruded with eaſier ſucceſs, or the contempt and disbelief of them by a fierce and inſolent urgency upon us, prove more coſtly and hazardous, than that, by which we now with ſo much ſecurity deride moſt important and ſignificant matters of fact!</p>
            <p>However, as to the truth and certainty of this joyous inſtance whoſe Funerals we now ſolemnize; I ſhall for once ſwear to it, in the words which the Pen of an Apoſtle hath already hallow'd for me;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, before God I lie not.</hi> I do ſpeak to you the <hi>words of truth and ſoberneſs,</hi> when I tell you that for ſome Years before this Gentleman was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from us, the bent and tendency of his life and actions was devout and religious. Such was his love to all publick Solemnities of Worſhip, that he ſeldom fail'd (and that not unleſs prevented by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or moſt indiſpenſible occaſions) his attendance every day at the Prayers of the Church, which himſelf alſo by a ſtated allowance, procur'd that they ſhould be every day perform'd. His carriage and demeanour in thoſe Services had ſo much the figure of a warm and tranſported devotion in it, that I could not forbear ſometimes caſting a glance at him, that by viewing him I might my ſelf excite and enkindle in my own boſom a new flame from the fire that ſeem'd to blaze ſo upon his Altars. His private intercourſe and communion with Heaven, I queſtion not but was very frequent and very rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous; becauſe, for ſome conſiderable time late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, I hardly ever could be alone with him, but he would be diſcourſing ſome Caſes of Conſcience about retir'd Cloſet-prayer, or the nature, neceſſity, or qualifications of a true and adequate repentance.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104694:12"/>I remember in his laſt ſickneſs, long before either himſelf or his Friends had any apprehenſions of the nearneſs of his end, when my ſelf in company with another
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. R. Kidder.</note> Reverend Perſon were giving him the viſit, he did with tears in his eyes, in ſtrange affectionateneſs bewail to us ſome perplexities of mind he then labour'd under; and that was, that he thought himſelf under a mighty incumbency to pray; and yet, ſuch was the ineptitude of his mind at that time through the indiſpoſition of his Body, that he could not think with that ſtrictneſs and collection of himſelf that becomes that Holy and Awful Majeſty to whom he was to pray; that what between the Conſcience he had of a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of praying, and the jealouſie upon himſelf leſt he ſhould not at that time perform it with all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Reverence and ſeriouſneſs, his mind was much harraſt and anxious what to do; For, <hi>Look you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my Conſcience is now as tender as wet Paper, torn upon every apprehenſion of the least guilt before GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Nature and Qualifications of an <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual</hi> Repentance in general, he made it the main of his buſineſs and ſtudy of late days to conſult the beſt and moſt diſtinct <hi>Authors</hi> and <hi>Treatiſes</hi> upon that Subject; and though he had as conductive an apprehenſion of things in his own large Mind as he could expect to meet with in Books, yet was he ſo humble and condeſcending, ſo little opiniona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of himſelf, that he would turn over any Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume that he believ'd did not trifle upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and ſometimes conſult ſome difficulties
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104694:13"/>even with my ſelf, whom, whiles he had reaſon to know he could inform and inſtruct, yet would he as humbly and obligingly enquire of as if he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſatisfaction in ſomething that had perplext him. To which purpoſe, I having ſometime ſince run through the Explication of the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> in ſeveral Diſcourſes, which he, through a long ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, had not been preſent at, excepting one or two that concluded the whole; he was ſo little in the thoughts of himſelf as to make it his requeſt to me, that I would go over thoſe Diſcourſes again in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, it having been a matter of his own ſtrict thought and enquiry a great while, what the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſignificancy, and diſtinct variety of thoſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions in that excellent form ſhould be.</p>
            <p>And as he much revolv'd the Nature and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of Repentance in general, ſo he would make the Application with ſeverity enough upon himſelf; more than once complaining to me, <hi>that he had a great jealouſie upon himſelf lest he had not yet conceived an horror anſwerable to his past exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitances of life, and had not made thoſe ſmart and pungent reflections upon himſelf, that might become one that had ſo long and in ſuch exalted degrees</hi> (as he ſaid) <hi>violated the Laws of his Maker, and made himſelf ſo obnoxious to the vengeance of his Judge.</hi> Yet even as to this he told me; <hi>that if the cutting off one of his Hands by the help of the other, were but a proper or likely way, through the anguiſh of ſuch a Wound, to give him a just horrour for his ſins, he would do that as willingly as he ever did any one action that had given him the greatest pleaſure of life.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104694:13"/>This he ſpake with that peculiar vehemency, that if there had been any ſtander by beſide my ſelf, he muſt readily have judg'd him to have been in earneſt. However he hath further told me, <hi>that he had thus far an aſſurance with himſelf that he had attained one of the main and most likely requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites in a ſolid and unfeigned repentance, that by the grace of God he had ſuch a ſenſe and conviction of the folly and unreaſonableneſs of ſin, that no argument, no temptation ſhould prevail upon him to do the like again.</hi> Which indeed amounts to the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition required and expected from the Penitent in the Holy Scriptures, and gives a juſt claim and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to that promiſe which aſſures us,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.13.</note> 
               <hi>that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſins ſhall have mercy.</hi> And in truth, I have reaſon to believe that his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to abridge himſelf in what formerly he had (perhaps) too liberally allowed himſelf in his too long and too intire abſtinences, made that change upon the <hi>craſis</hi> and habit of his Body that haſten'd <hi>his end</hi> and <hi>our grief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had for many years practis'd in the <hi>Politicks</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> and having ſo nearly attacht himſelf to one of the greateſt
<note place="margin">E. Clarend. L. Ch.</note> Miniſters of State that this Kingdom ever knew (whoſe miſtaken Wiſdom and Integrity perhaps hath been ſince better underſtood by the want of him) made himſelf no ſmall Figure in the adminiſtration: wherein (I muſt needs ſay) I never perceiv'd his Conſcience reflecting upon him the reproach of any injuſtice and unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Counſel or Action; but as he always aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyl'd himſelf in that, ſo I never heard of any Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104694:14"/>that objected it againſt him. Yet did he for many years before his death make a voluntary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat from all the buſineſs, or preferments, that even needed and courted him, and after his reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very from a long and dangerous ſickneſs, which hath given him above two years reſpit of life ſince, he told me he burnt all his Papers, all his obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and memorials that had any relation with politicks or buſineſs of State, that he might lye under no temptation of diverting his mind from that retirement within it ſelf to which he had now reduc'd and devoted it; being of that Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher's mind, who tells us <hi>how foreign and alienated a thing all true good is from a buſling encumber'd state of life:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which, how unhappy a loſs ſoever, ſuch a flame that devour'd ſuch Papers, might occaſion to the World, yet was it an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment indeed, how vehemently this <hi>Great Mind</hi> breath'd and enlarg'd it ſelf toward Heaven the only Centre of its reſt and ſatisfaction; which ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thought ſometimes would comfort him, and ſtrengthen his hopes of acceptance with God, (as he hath expreſt himſelf to me) <hi>viz.</hi> that, <hi>that grace and clemency of God that had thus reduc'd, and in any meaſure recover'd him to himſelf, would overlook his former Errors of life, and steer and conduct him ſucceſsfully the remainder of his days, till he ſhould enter him into his own joys:</hi> And of this no doubt he would have given us encouraging aſſurances before he had wholly quitted us, but that the firſt paroxyſm in his ſickneſs that gave us any appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of his death, depriv'd him of his intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104694:14"/>and afterward of his ſpeech, that we could reap none of the expected advantages of either; but only ſome lucid intervals we might gueſs, by the devout motion and deportment of himſelf, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we might ſuppoſe him importunately engag'd in Prayers that were <hi>unutterable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much may ſerve as to that firſt quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in the <hi>Text,</hi> that adorn'd this Gentleman, and hath made our deprivement of him ſo deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that is, his <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> or <hi>Religion toward GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall make but a brief mention of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſs or Charity toward Men; not that it was ſo <hi>ſmall and inconſiderable,</hi> that it will bear but a ſlender and tranſient <hi>Encomium.</hi> For it was large and diffuſive indeed, but for the moſt part ſo ſilent and unboaſted, that it generally ran deepeſt where it made no noiſe; and I am ſure would have been moſt pleaſing to him (could he have been ſenſible of this ſolemnity) had it not been mention'd at all. But to paſs over the liberal expences he hath been at, in making both beautiful and uſeful the Place of our Worſhip with the appendages to it; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear recognizing one ſubſtantial inſtance of his Charity, becauſe it had a double reach, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the advantage of the Body, but the Soul too: For he hath ſetled an Annual encouragement for ever, for the reading of Publick Prayers every Morning in the Week, and Twelve Pence to be every Morning diſtributed amongſt the Poor that are preſent there.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104694:15"/>
What ſhall I add more? May I not uſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's complaint in part, that <hi>the righteous and the merciful man is taken from us?</hi> But muſt I uſe it all? <hi>that no man layeth it to heart, no man conſidereth that he is taken away from the evil to come?</hi> God forbid. The poor ſurely <hi>will lay it to heart,</hi> when they ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly find one of their main Springs dry'd up that was wont by very ſecret and unobſerv'd conveyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ſupply and refreſh them. The Good Man ſurely will <hi>conſider</hi> the ſtroke, as what ſeems to have ſenſible diſpleaſure in it; and as he is depriv'd of an Example and Companion in Goodneſs: and I would to God we might All improve it, that by our repentance under ſuch a chaſtiſement, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully writing after ſo great a Copy and Pattern he hath ſet, we may both turn off the <hi>approaching evil</hi> which he ſeems <hi>taken away from,</hi> and attain the ſame Joys and Rewards of Goodneſs which we have good hopes he is now inſtated in. <hi>Which God of his infinite mercy grant, through our Lord Jeſus Christ, to whom with Himſelf and his Holy Spirit, be aſcrib'd all Glory and Praiſe for ever.</hi> Amen!</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104694:15"/>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104694:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:104694:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
